[Music]
This is software engineering radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by its software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
[Music]
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host Jeff Doolittle. This
episode will explore the role of human
programmers in the AI era. Topics around
machine learning and AI have come up
frequently in previous episodes. Some
examples are episode 633 with Itamar
Freriedman on automated testing with
generative AI. Episode 63 hosted Rish
Singh on using Genai for test code
generation. And in episode 626, EPZ
Oskaya joined software engineering radio
again to discuss Gen AI for software
architecture. Today we're hosting Arty
Chevchenko who is a former Google
software engineer, exceed and founder of
a startup. Currently he's a software
engineer at Canva and a lecturer at ITMO
University which is famous for winning
more programming world cups than any
other university in the world. He is
also the author of the recently
published book Code Health Guardian, the
old new role of human programmers in the
AI era. Arty, welcome to the show.
>> Thanks for having me. Glad you're here.
The subtitle of your book, as I said, is
the old new role of human programmers in
the AI era. In your view, what does it
take for programmers to be successful in
the era of AI?
I think there are three things you need
to be great at. One is collaborating
with AI. Another is delegating to AI.
These two are very much on the hype
right now. Everybody talks about Copilot
and Cursor, I guess. But there is also
one more thing there. You really want to
be better than AI at something. And if
we were talking about software
engineers, I would say your best bet is
to become an expert in managing code
complexity. Just because complex
reasoning is hard for AI and in software
engineering, that's probably the hardest
problem we have. How do we keep our code
bases reasonably simple? So yeah,
honestly I wouldn't over focus on
learning these AI tools like cursor and
copilot today and really spend some time
to make sure that you're ready for this
new role of human software engineers
which is code health guardian that's how
I call it and that's the title of the
book. So you mentioned the idea of
complexity. In case it's unclear to our
listeners, help us connect. How does
complexity relate to this idea that you
describe about programmers as code
health guardians?
>> Yeah, definitely. When I say code
health, I basically mean code that is
simple enough, code that is reasonably
simple or maintainable.
So if that's the hardest problem in
software engineering to keep our code
bases simple enough then it's likely
that we will continue to be better than
AI in this for at least some time maybe
years maybe even decades so yeah that's
basically the link there
>> why does AI struggle to keep things
simple in your experience
>> complex reasoning is hard for AI so it
looks simple on the surface often I I
think that's what AI is very good at. It
gives you an impression that it
understands things, right? And it gives
you an impression that okay, that's
super simple. It's like 1 2 3 here you
go. But sometimes the real world has
very significant challenges that need to
be deeply understood and that's what
humans still do better than AI at this
point. So would you say sometimes the AI
comes up with simplistic solutions
rather than simple ones? Okay. Okay. So
your contention is that humans still
need to maintain the sense of complexity
management and the way we do it is by
guarding the health of our code.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> And you mentioned maintainability. Are
there other aspects to code health? You
mentioned simplicity and
maintainability. How else would you
characterize code that is healthy?
>> That's basically the definition. If
we're talking about definitions, I just
use the term health as an alternative to
saying that is reasonably simple or
pragmatically simple. But I like to
think about code health as a
productivity question. I think it is
ultimately a productivity question. So
if you think about human productivity or
programmers productivity, the first
thing that comes to mind is team
productivity, right? There are a bunch
of factors that make team either
productive or not productive like
psychological safety, reliability, clear
goals, clear responsibilities, impact,
all these kind of things. But if we zoom
in a little bit into an individual in a
team, still in a reasonably productive
team, you will have individuals which
perform really great and individuals
that perform not that great. And
historically, if you're an engineering
manager dealing with this issue, the
question you're asking yourself is,
well, is it a skill problem or is it a
will problem, right? But I find that
often the answer to this question is no.
It may be all good with skills and it
may be all good with the will. So for
me, I don't think I ever had any major
issues with the will problems or skill
problems. For me, I definitely had some
issues with finding the right balance
between long-term and short-term
productivity.
And that's what I call term
productivity. It's pretty hard to talk
without any visuals. But if you can
imagine having a spectrum where on the
left side it is short-term productivity
and on the right side it is long-term
productivity. If you're too focused on
the long-term productivity, it's kind of
obvious why you're not productive
because you're often planning to be
productive in the future, right?
>> Someday I'll be productive, right?
>> Yeah. And uh if you're focused too much
on the short term, you become too
tactical. you create too much complexity
along the way and that's what AI agents
could do for us too. And you really want
to have the balance there. You want to
care about users needs right now to
deliver now but also care about user
needs like a year from now so that you
don't create too much complexity so that
you cannot execute in a year from now.
>> Right. So a few interesting insights
from that one. You didn't seem to say
that long-term or short-term is better.
There's a balance between long and
short-term productivity. Did I
understand that correctly?
>> Yeah, that's correct. And definitely
there are times when you need to focus
on the short term for several weeks or
maybe even months and just deliver.
There are times when you need to focus
more on long-term, but in general, you
need to find the healthy balance between
these two extremes and be somewhere in
the middle.
>> Okay. And then the other aspect I think
you're implying as well is that it's
humans job to ensure long-term
productivity. That AI might make us
short-term productive, but that at least
as it currently stands, it's not going
to solve the problem for us of long-term
productivity. Is that correct?
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> Okay, great. Well, that might lead
really well into my next question, which
is what motivated you to write Code
Health Guardian? Well, I guess I was
always passionate about knowledge
sharing. So, even starting with my uni
years, I remember we were doing classes
for high school students and even
primary school students a little bit and
right now I'm teaching in university
doing university classes. So, yeah, this
passion for knowledge sharing was pretty
much always there. But in terms of this
particular book, I guess there are three
key events there apart from doing
university classes which definitely
prepared me for writing this book
because they inspired the content of
those classes inspired the content of
the book very very much. But there are
two other key events I would mention.
The first one is doing good code
reviewer internal classes at Google. So
the story there is that when I was at
Google, I was pretty much every day I
was just spending a little bit of time
reading random documentation and at some
point I started realizing that there is
so much information about how to do code
reviews on our internet and I just
wanted to consolidate all of that. So
that's what I did. I just consolidated
all of that, created a single slide deck
for that. And at some point that slide
deck became pretty popular and I even
started getting requests from other
Googlers asking whether there are any
tech talks about this, if there are any
classes about this. So I started doing
the good code reviewer classes
internally at Google and that was pretty
successful. I think in just one year we
had over a thousand Googlers, software
engineers who went through those
classes. We got like astonishing 4.5
rating based on over 100 reviews and
that's really golden standard at Google
for tech talks. Like you know when we're
doing on boarding that's roughly the
rating you get for those on boarding
classes and like if you can if you can
reach 4.5 that's kind of that means
you've done a good job.
>> Yeah. So yeah, that was the first key
event doing those classes. It gave me
quite a lot of confidence I guess to
start university courses later. The
second key event was John Asterhood book
presentation in Google's Sunnyville
office. So I just randomly ended up
being there. I had no idea what to
expect. I guess it was just advertised
by some internal channels and I ended up
being in that room just knowing that
some guy is going to present on his
software engineering book. And when he
was talking about software engineering
and complexity and complexity causes and
complexity symptoms as he called them,
that really resonated with me and was
like, "Oh yeah, that really makes
sense." And yeah then when I was
starting the university classes I think
to a large extent maybe up to 50% the
initial content of those university
courses was actually based on John's
book philosophy of software design. Also
of course my own experience at Google
and a bunch of other books like
pragmatic programmer but John's book was
very very key.
>> That's great. And I'll put a link in the
show notes to software engineering radio
episode 520 where I interviewed John
Osterhout about his book a philosophy of
software design. So that'll be good for
listeners to be able to dig into. So a
lot of our guests on the show have
written books and my understanding
having not published a book myself is
that it can be challenging. So what
helped you to stick with it along the
way?
>> Yeah, it was a long long process. I
started it in 2022. At that point,
software engineering at Google book was
already published and a bunch of things
that I've learned internally at Google.
I was surprised that they were not
covered because I was expecting it to be
a lot about actually coding and software
design and all this stuff how we do this
internally at Google. But if you take a
look at the Flamingo book, there is not
much about it there. It's mostly about
building engineering organization.
>> Okay.
>> So that gave me a feeling that there is
a an opportunity there. Already at that
point I been iterating on the university
classes for quite a long time. So I've
had quite a lot of insights into how to
communicate complex topics in a simple
way but also some unique insights about
software design as well. And in 2022
when I suddenly got quite a lot of time
I decided to start writing the book. So
I did a couple of chapters and one of
the chapters was on design docs. So I
reached out to Max Canada Alexander the
author of code simplicity with that
draft asking for his feedback. And I
guess that's one of the turning points
when you want to get support from
somebody because you're kind of like
you're just starting and you're not
completely sure how will it go. And what
Max did he actually referred me to Titus
Winters who was saying look for this you
probably need to talk to Titus. He was
curating software engineering at Google
and he can give you a feedback for this.
So that's what I did. I asked him for a
warm intro. He did me a warm winter and
I sent it to Titus and Titus was so
supportive. He looked through the
chapter draft and said that well look it
looks great. For different reasons, we
decided to keep the design docs section
in software engineer and Google pretty
short. But yeah, it's definitely worth
making it public and talking about this
to which I responded to him saying like,
"Hey, do you want to write this
together, write this book together,
maybe overly ambitious, but at that
point I already went through the YC
combinator startup school and was
running a startup. So like I was a
little bit pushy, but Titus said like
that would be great. That's a great
project, but I don't really have time
for this.
>> Anyway, Titus support was very important
in the beginning. I guess that what
>> made me brave enough to continue working
on it. I guess the second turning point
was when after a year of writing, I
realized that the scope is a little bit
too big, you know, because originally
the name of the book was productive
software engineering. That's what I
wanted to That's the name of the
university. Broad
>> it is. Yeah, but that's the university
course and I was thinking maybe I I
would just publish my university course
and it has two parts. It has this
technical part which is about code
complexity and there is like
nontechnical part
>> but after a year I realized yeah that's
too much. So it would be talmud if if
you can say it in English
>> right that's the word
>> yeah a very very long book so I've
reduced the scope and decided to focus
solely on code health and decided let it
be a story of a healthy codebase so that
was the second part that really helped
actually complete this work and the
third one the third turning point not a
turning point but I received a lot of
support from tech reviewers So that's
something I didn't expect, but there
were so many like dozens of people who
left a bunch of comments on the
manuscript and helped to make this book
much better. So yeah, I guess these
three events or turning points.
>> Great. Can you share a real world
example of a project or a team that
neglected code health and it led to
significant productivity issues?
>> Yeah, sure. I think actually these
stories is what made me truly pragmatic
and truly care about code health to be
like strategic about code complexity not
on one of the extremes on the term
productivity spectrum and that's story
is from my startup from the company I
was running I think that was really
really motivating not only because I as
a CEO cared about product so much and
productivity but also that because it
was a self-funded startup. So, I was
actually paying engineers
>> to do the work. So, if you see having
productivity issues, you have really
good incentives to fix it. And we had
problems on both sides of the spectrum.
We definitely had problems on the to
clean code approach like more kind of a
long-term investing in the long-term
productivity when both on the back end I
was spending too much time on stuff that
didn't matter that much especially in
the startup world where you need to
iterate so fast
>> but on the front end side I also saw
front end engineers building some sort
of frameworks and reinventing wheels and
being kind of strategic about what
they're doing but That's not what we
wanted and we needed to iterate. We
needed to get feedback from customers
very quickly. So yeah, that's on that
side of the spectrum. But interestingly,
we had problems on the other side of the
spectrum as well. So sometimes they
would just iterate and deliver stuff.
But after a year I think or so front end
engineers came to me and said like one
of the key pages I wanted changes on,
they just couldn't do that. They just
couldn't deliver that. They were just
telling me, you know, like it's too
complicated. I'm doing something. I'm
breaking something and I don't really
understand what I'm doing anymore. And
we had to start from the beginning. So,
we had problems on each side of the
spectrum, which was pretty interesting.
>> Yeah, that's fascinating. So, you're
basically saying there was sometimes too
much long-term thinking and too much
short-term thinking at the same time.
>> Yeah, I guess in in different parts, in
different projects.
>> In different parts. Yeah.
>> And so there's a balance you have to
strike. You need some long-term
strategic thinking. You need some
short-term iterating, but you have to
apply it appropriately in the
appropriate contexts.
>> Yeah, you
>> that's a tricky balance.
>> It is a tricky balance.
>> How do you strike that balance?
>> I believe the easiest way and how it
worked for me is the ownership
mentality. Honestly,
>> ah well that's the other thing I was
going to highlight that you said it was
your money.
>> Yeah, exactly.
>> So tell Yeah. So tell us more about
that. That's interesting. What exactly
do you want to hear?
>> Well, you know, I had a mentor of mine
tell me that if you want to increase
your engineering outcomes, you should
treat the company's money like it's your
own money. And it sounds like you're
basically saying the same thing.
>> So, how did it change things for you
when it was your money?
>> Yeah, as I mentioned, you care about
productivity not only because of the
product. You start caring about
productivity also because you're
actually spending money on this. I don't
think you can apply this to many
software engineers because they're not
paying their money for what they're
doing. But I think what is realistic to
expect is still to have this ownership
mentality like be kind of a product
owners. I think that's the only way to
truly strike the balance there because
if we're saying okay and I've read it
somewhere too like it's uh product
manager's job to care about the product
and it's software engineer's job to care
about code quality so that you can
continue iterating in the future right
but I don't think it's a perfectly valid
statement because once you do that it's
kind of a distributed responsibility and
you have this push and pull and depends
on who pushes harder and it's like it's
pretty tricky because product managers
wouldn't have half of the story right
they're not exposed to the code base
they cannot reason about the tech depth
and all that stuff so I think the only
good solution here is for engineers to
be more product focused to be more like
a product owners and engineers have much
higher chances of having a full picture
>> do you have an example of an engineer
who did a good job of learning how to
think more like a product manager and
how that helped them be more successful.
I had a colleague at Google who had a A4
paper printed in front of her and above
her desk there was a paper saying user
problem is bigger than engineering
problem and honestly I think every
engineer should have such poster at
least in their head and always remember
that ultimately what we're doing the
ultimate cause for this is to build
products and to help our users. If you
can remind yourself about this
regularly, I think inevitably you will
be more productive, you'll be more
product focused and will be motivated to
find the right balance on that term
productivity spectrum.
Great. So I think we have a general
sense of the answer to this next
question, but maybe give us some more
specifics on how you selected the topics
that you cover in the book and then
we'll dive more into some of those
topics. Yeah, it happened very
organically. As I mentioned before, the
book is a story of a healthy codebase.
So every chapter of the book is an
important part of the story. So when I
was about to start the book, I already
knew pretty much the name of every
chapter and more or less the content of
every chapter. And there are two parts.
If you look in the first part, it is
structured around uh code complexity
model about three complexity problems.
Change amplification cognition.
>> Well, we'll talk we'll talk about them.
We'll talk about them. But
>> yeah, I'll just mention them here. So
unknown un no unknowns and there are
seven complexity causes and then there
are multiple chapters. All the other
chapters from part one address one or
two of those complexity causes. So
chapter 3 is mostly design by contract
is mostly about true interfaces. Chapter
four is about simple interfaces. Chapter
five is about having too many
dependencies and application. Chapter
six also about too many dependencies.
Chapter 7 is mostly about obscurity. So
that's basically how the first part is
structured and then there is also the
second part which is about code related
processes the key code related
processes. It is about design docs about
trade-off analysis about code review and
build versus buy decisions. And the
reason there is this second part is that
code health starts outside of code. And
if you want to tell the story of a
healthy codebase, you need to talk about
these code related processes as well.
There's an interesting related story
actually from Google. I didn't invent
the term code health. It is actually the
name of a working group internally at
Google and I've heard that when they
were discussing how to name that group,
they were thinking about naming it
something like code quality or something
like this. But the reason for choosing
the name code health was that a lot of
the responsibilities of that working
group was actually about these key code
related processes like code review. And
for the very same reason there is a
second part in this book because if we
want to talk about code health, we need
to talk about code related processes as
well. Code health starts outside of
code. So to summarize a couple things
you said, it it sounds like a lot of
what we're talking about here is how do
we get productivity towards solving user
problems and how do we do it in a
sustainable way. So if we're too
shortsighted, we can get productivity
quickly, but then we can slow down. And
if we're too long-term thinking, we may
never get the productivity we want in
the first place. We have to balance
those forces. Is that a good summary of
what we've discussed so far?
>> Yeah, that's a good summary. I think
that's one of the qualities of this book
that is very pragmatic in some ways
maybe even more pragmatic than pragmatic
programmer that we really want to strike
a perfect balance. It took me a long
time to be balanced myself and to be
more pragmatic and I just wanted to
share my experience about that.
>> Okay. Well then let's dive in. You
mentioned as we you know start moving
through some of the topics in the book
the three problems of complexity and you
mentioned before high cognitive load
change amplification and unknown
unknowns. Can you describe what those
mean and then give the listeners some
concrete examples of what happens when
we don't address those three problems in
real software projects?
>> Yeah, sure. So you probably have heard
about these complexity problems if
you're familiar with John Auster's work.
So these are change amplification,
cognitive load and unknown unknowns. He
calls them complexity symptoms but I
actually think they're actual practical
problems we're dealing with. So the
first one I started with the least
severe problem it is change
amplification and it's basically when
your small change which you think will
be a small change is amplified and it
actually results in a huge PR like
hundreds of lines of code across dozens
of files something like that.
>> Say that again. So it affects hundreds
of lines of code across dozens of files.
Yeah, it's kind of a you expected it to
be simple and simple change in a single
file or in a couple of files but
>> and it just ripples throughout the
entire codebase.
>> Exactly.
>> Okay. So that's change amplification.
>> It is change amplification but it is the
least severe of the complexity problems.
There is a very nice diagram in the book
in chapter 2 which connects complexity
problems to productivity problems.
Right. Now, least severe doesn't mean
it's not severe. It just means it's less
severe than the other two.
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> Okay.
>> And it depends on the scale, right? If
you if you if you have like two
duplicates and there is no obscurity
around that they duplicate each other,
you're probably fine. You can you can
change it in two places or three places.
It just affects the development speed.
But development speed is just one of the
productivity problems. There are more
productivity problems which are probably
more important like buggy products.
>> Before before we talk about those real
quick, I will put a link in the show
notes to a previous episode with Vlad
Konov where we talked about balancing
coupling and software design and he
talks a lot about how you would handle
this kind of change amplification. So
we'll include that in the show notes. So
change amplification is the least
severe. It doesn't mean it's not severe.
What's the next most severe of those
three problems of complexity?
>> Yeah. So just let me let me finish
answering to the previous one.
>> Ah yes that's right sure
>> because it is the least severe because
it only affects development speed but
there is also another productivity
problem which is buggy product. We don't
have any bugs in the product. Another
productivity problem is developer
exhaustion. So the problem with these
problems is that if you look at the
graph they are all very much
interconnected with each other.
developer exhaustion, bugs, and code
complexity. And there are a bunch of
vicious cycles there. So, it's kind of
reinforces itself.
>> And if we're talking about change
amplification, it's kind of isolated in
this productivity diagram. It doesn't
participate in these productivity
regression vicious cycles. That's my
understanding why it's the least severe
problem. And there are nice
visualizations in the book about it. And
I think I agree with John Oood here. So,
we're on the same page. I'm pretty sure
he says the same thing like change
amplification is the least severe there.
>> Again, it's not that it isn't severe,
it's just not the most severe.
>> Yeah. It depends on the scale.
>> Right. Right. Right. That exactly. Okay.
>> Then the next one is cognitive load. And
that's something you typically think of
when you hear code complexity. So that's
what you're thinking. Okay, that's takes
too much effort to understand this code
to actually digest what is happening
here. That's basically cognitive load.
Well, that could probably be subject to
competing forces as well, couldn't it?
Like maybe I mean what could that look
like? 10,000 lines in a single function.
Would you call that cognitive load
perhaps?
>> Yeah, definitely. Definitely. Yeah,
because you need to understand all the
dependencies between lines there, I
guess. But then what about if I split
that up into like 20 different services
and then I inject them all into one
thing? That could be the opposite end of
the spectrum where I've maybe over
decomposed and that would also increase
cognitive load.
>> Yeah, there are definitely different
ways in which you can achieve this. You
can make things complicated in many
different ways.
>> Many different ways. Well, as Neil Ford
has said, developers are drawn to
complexity like moths to a flame, often
with the same outcome. So this is how it
goes.
>> Yeah. But it is really bad having high
cognitive load. You may need to spend
many hours to actually understand what's
going on. Sometimes you may not be able
to understand it yourself but probably
you will find somebody who can
understand hopefully. So yeah that's
kind of a attributes of this cognitive
load problem is bad but it's not the
worst.
>> Mhm. So the worst is coming. Yeah.
>> Yeah. The worst is still coming. The
worst is unknown unknowns and that's
basically when you do not have some
information that you really need to
accomplish a task at hand. So if you
want to do something but you do not know
where to start or even worse you don't
know what you need to know to do this
correctly. So there is some obscurity
involved here.
>> So can you give me an example of you
just said for example there's something
I need to know but I don't know that I
need to know. Has this happened to you
or to team members maybe that you've
worked with in your startup where you
discovered later that the actual issue
that you were struggling with was
unknown unknowns? Yeah, there was an
interesting story that happened to us in
Google Maps, my first team at Google. At
some point we had a very senior engineer
joined our team and he actually joined
us as an engineering manager but I guess
at some point he was bored because it
was mostly a maintenance project that we
were working on and I guess because of
that he was looking through the code and
he deleted some configuration for our
bad jobs and the comment on that PR was
literally something like you don't need
all this stuff like this should all be
done automatically. It was about
choosing the right data centers for
masters and for slaves for our batch
jobs which are basically improved map
producers. You can think about it like
this. And what happened is one morning
literally all of our batch jobs like 20
of them started sending us an alert
saying that we cannot start the job
cannot be started. These are daily jobs
and we kind of started because the drops
for yesterday are still running and yeah
getting these alerts I fairly quickly
realized what's going on. The choices
for masters and slaves for their jobs
were all very very poor and all those
jobs were in like previous stages just
choosing one node in North America
another node in Europe and like trying
to send all the data between them and
that's because automation didn't work.
He was correct that ideally if those
jobs were written from scratch, it all
should have happened automatically. But
these were very old jobs that were
written like 5 years ago or something
like that. And at that point there was
no automation and it required manual
choices and it was really fancy logic.
It was really complicated. It took me
quite a lot of time to really dig down
into like how it worked. And I actually
wrote a pretty long page internal that
was explaining how these configuration
parameters are working which became
pretty popular actually but he just went
ahead and deleted that part of
configuration and there are two
learnings there. One is that you
shouldn't delete something that you
don't understand why is it there in the
first place and that's what is called
chester and pants and we can talk about
this but there's also another problem
there that there were no comments in
those configuration files explaining why
do you need all of this configuration
how does it work so I can definitely
relate to him being confused about it
and trying to do something about it
Okay.
>> Can your software engineering team plan,
track, and ship faster? Monday Dev says
yes. With Monday Dev, you get fully
customizable workflows, AI powered
context, and integrations that work
within your IDE. No more admin
bottlenecks, no add-ons, no BS, just a
frictionless platform built for
developers. Try for free at
monday.com/dev.
You'll love it.
So next in the book you explore the
seven causes of complexity. So describe
for listeners what these seven causes
are and then how these tend to show up
in a codebase because the goal here as
you've said is to create people who are
guardians of code health. And to do that
we need to understand complexity. So
what are these sources and what would we
see in a codebase where we're not
properly considering these seven causes
of complexity?
>> Yeah, sure. So let's go over them in the
order of decreasing severity roughly. So
the first one is obscurity and we
already started talking about this. The
previous
>> unknown unknowns. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Unknown unknown stuff. The
previous example is
missing documentation, missing comments.
That's a very common example of
obscurity. But obscurity is so general.
It manifests in so many different ways.
It can be obscure naming. That's another
very popular manifestation of obscurity.
But also there are things that are
really hard to avoid and even it can be
a necessary trade-off obscurity. For
example, if you're thinking about
eventdriven design, it necessarily has
some obscurity in it. If you're trying
to debug stuff and you're trying to
reconstruct the chain of events that
caused this thing, like that's that's
not an easy thing to do, right? There is
some inherent obscurity there. And
sometimes you intentionally agree to
have an obscurity, but as much as
possible, I guess it's better to avoid
it. The next one would probably be
complex interfaces. Complex interfaces
probably don't need any any description,
right? It's kind of intuitive, but the
problem with them is that actually cause
all three complexity problems. So if
we're thinking about change
amplification or cognitive load unknown
unknowns, all of that can be caused by
having complex interfaces. this be an
interface with lots of operations or
maybe the operations don't they're not
cohesive they don't belong together
these kinds of things.
>> Yeah. And even like having too many
parameters in an interface is not
>> too many parameters. Yeah.
>> Like confusing confusing name and yeah
quite a lot of different things can go
wrong with interfaces. But there are
interfaces that appear simple. They can
be simple to read and understand, but
they still can be complicated. They can
be hard to use. For example, if you
think about assembler, assembler is most
of the commands the commands, they're
pretty simple, right? It's easy to
understand what they're doing. But if
you want to do something assembler, even
device drivers, they're not being done
as simpler these days, right? Because
that's too complicated. You need to
learn all those patterns, how to use
these simple interfaces to do anything
useful.
>> So yeah, simple interfaces are about not
being simple to read and understand but
also about simple to use as well. Yeah,
we had an interesting story internally
at Google. We were very passionate about
implementing a complete crowd API at
some point and we were talking about
this like delete update create all those
methods and spent quite a lot of time
doing this and then later realized that
actually the teams two teams that were
using them they didn't need this
granular API they actually wanted like
more specific APIs that would address
their use cases but we were just going
forward with this clean approach to
provide a full API which doesn't make
sense in the high side. So I'm really
really cautious about building something
that would solve any problem. Just use
it however you want to use it. This kind
of arguments are not the best. You can
end up with having very flexible API
that doesn't really help.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Sometimes you need that,
right? If you're writing a public API
and truly do not understand what it will
be used for and you want to give uh
developers some freedom to experiment
and build whatever comes to their mind.
But often that's not the case. Often
when we're building an API, we already
know what are the internal use cases for
that and we just need to spend some time
to make it not just appear simple and be
easy to understand but also be easy to
use as well. Yeah, that's a good call
out to a previous episode I did with
Yuval Loey on his book writing software
and everything about his methodology is
about driving things via the use cases.
So, we'll put a link to that in the show
notes as well cuz you called out use
cases a couple times. So, that made me
that made me think about that as well.
So, we've talked about obscurity, we
talked about complex interfaces. We
don't necessarily need to go through all
seven causes of complexity because
listeners can get the book and then we
can continue on. But were there any
other causes of complexity that you
wanted to highlight where maybe they
affected a team that you were working
with or or maybe a team successfully
addressed one of these causes and it was
noteworthy?
>> Yeah, I think one of the causes that I
see being addressed really well at
Canva, that's where I'm working right
now, is unfamiliarity. So just
historically, Canva was very good about
keeping things consistent, especially
when Canva was smaller. Right now it's a
bit more challenging. And that kind of
makes sense too because if you think
about consistency, the first thing
you're need to understand is whether
it's consistency about code style or
consistent about code quality. If you're
talking about code styles, it's simple,
right? You just have a code style. have
a proper formatter used by everyone and
it just works. It's great value for
money. But if we're talking about code
quality, it's a bit more complicated.
The next question is whether we're
talking about consistency across like
the whole organization, the whole code
base or are we talking about consistency
specifically within a team. So if your
organization is smaller, it's more like
a team consistency than organization and
it's much easier to communicate those
global rules and make sure they are
consistently applied across the
codebase. But in general, the value,
especially as the company grows, the
value kind of decreases because you do
not work in other teams code bases as
often. And also it's so hard to
communicate those rules and be
consistent about them. So across the
company it becomes a bit challenging and
the value for money is probably not that
good. But if we're talking about
consistency within a team, I think
that's very very important because the
value is much higher. you're actually
working on the same code base and the
cost is much lower because you have just
a few folks you need to agree with and
make sure that you communicated those
rules and you just be consistent about
how you do things in your codebase. One
global rule that we have at Canva and
which I personally now benefit a lot
because I work on the authorization
project is that access checkers are very
well structured. there is a well-
definfined structure of access checks
across the whole company. So it means
that we can actually improve this over
time because it is consistent for
different teams. If it wasn't if every
team was doing access checks in their
own way, it just wouldn't be possible.
>> I think a lot of people are doing access
checks in their own way. So that might
be uh something that they could learn
from.
Let's move on to discuss some design
principles for code health. So you know
there's a lot of books written about
principles and practices and you
mentioned specifically some design
principles. So let's talk about what
those are and then how those can affect
code health.
>> You're opening in Pandora box honestly
because
I guess I could answer with half of the
book's content.
>> Yes. Each one of these could be an
episode unto its own but just give
listeners a taste like design by
contract for example. What does that
mean and how does that help with code
health? Yeah, sure. Design by contract
is very crucial because you need to
trust interfaces if you want to keep
your code reasonably simple. If you do
not trust interfaces, if there is not
enough information in the interface
itself or if you cannot trust it like
you end up adding quite a lot of
complexity into a code to just get
around it and you know just have those
safety nets. So it's really costly thing
not to have interfaces that you can
trust. And I think the only way to solve
this trust problem is to follow the
design by contract paradigm. It's a
pretty old one, right? And I probably
don't need to explain what it is. You
might actually because you know every
year there's new people in the software
industry. So you know some of our
listeners who are new to the industry
may not be familiar with it. So if you
don't mind give us just a brief, you
know, you mentioned interfaces and
contracts. How do those relate? What
what is design by contract? I think it
all starts with modular design and I
will use the term module as John Oihood
use it basically anything that has an
interface and implementation. I think it
goes all the way back to Paras's
definition.
>> It does. A module is something with an
interface inputs outputs and inside it
should be a black box. So it could be a
function and it could be a system and
anything in between.
>> Yeah. But then if you want to models to
be useful, if you want your
decomposition to not look like fu which
calls fu 1, fu 2, fu 3, fu 4, like you
really need to decompose it meaningfully
and then have clear contracts for the
other modules that you're calling from
the implementation. So that's where
design by contract really comes into
play. It's kind of obvious things, but
it's about being explicit about what the
module does, documenting whatever is
missing from the code, just writing down
as documentation
and then internally enforcing those
contracts internally in the module. So
if you provide a class that has an
interface, it is your responsibility to
actually test that implementation that
it actually does what the interface
promises to do. So that's basically the
crux of the design contract. You
document what this model is doing and
you internally enforce it. It's only not
only about tests. Assertions also is a
huge part of it. They're especially
useful for enforcing preconditions.
Design a contract as a term was coined
by Beton Mayor when he was working on
his AEL language and he used the terms
precondition, postcond condition and
cluster I believe. So basically the way
he was putting it is that if all the
preconditions are met then the module
guarantees that all the post conditions
will be met after the call and that all
the invariance would still hold. So
basically that's I think roughly the
definition he was given and yeah when
we're talking about assertions they in
particular help with validating the
preconditions in runtime. I think uh
pragmatic programmer makes a very good
point about assertions saying that it is
naive to rely on tests only because yes
you need good test coverage and that's
definitely the main contract enforcement
mechanism but apart from tests there are
billions of different states your
program will go through in production in
runtime. So having assertions in runtime
actually is complimentary to having good
test coverage.
>> That's interesting. You said there could
be billions of states your system could
be in. So effectively it sounds like
you're making the case that assertions
are another strategy for handling
complexity.
>> Yeah, exactly. It's it's a strategy for
enforcing contracts that at least all
the preconditions are really met in your
production system,
>> right? and reducing the number of
possible states that your system can be
in to ones that you are aware of. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's if you do not do that, you
will end up with having extra logic
handling those edge cases. But so often
you just need to say, hey, this code
wasn't intended to be used with such an
input. So you just fail fast and that's
the best thing you can do. You simplify
the code. you don't handle those edge
cases and you make sure that the system
if it is alive it is in a correct state.
>> Yeah, it's interesting. I think young
software engineers often try to swallow
exceptions for example and pretend they
didn't happen but more mature engineers
want an exception to bring the system
down and that's essentially what you
just described there. Yeah, there are
definitely cases when you want a safety
net. Like in particular, if you're
having an important operation that is
followed by some sort of a cleanup or
optional operation that can be handled
later, maybe you want to wrap it in a
try catch, but in general, yeah, I 100%
agree that yeah, you don't want to mask
errors. Let's talk about dry. We talk
about one of the principles for code
health. You have some interesting takes
on by dry I mean the don't repeat
yourself principle and I think some
people maybe take this to the extreme
but you I think have a more nuanced
perspective on this. So talk about the
dry principle how it relates to code
health and how to balance just how dry
you should actually seek to be in your
codebase.
>> Yeah that's one of the takeaways I hope
from this book is that complexity is not
a single problem. There are actually
three different problems, change
amplification, cognitive load, and
unknown unknowns. And they all have
different severity. So if we're talking
about dry principal violations, the
worst problem there is not change
amplifications even though it's the most
obvious one. The worst one is unknown
unknowns. So when it becomes really
really bad is when you do not really
know that there is a duplicate somewhere
else. It may look differently. It may be
different code, but it's kind of a still
a knowledge duplicate, right? And if you
do not know that there is a duplicate,
then you're in a bad state because these
duplicates can over time they can start
diverging and that's the way towards
driving your system crazy having
diverged duplicates which are not really
duplicates anymore. So if you can get
rid of the unknown unknowns problems, I
think you're already good enough. So we
had this tooling practice at Google and
tooling for marking the duplicates in
code. Often it would be different
languages like front end and back end
basically saying if you change this then
change this. And if you have such
comments in code then basically you've
addressed the unknown unknowns problem.
There is no obscurity anymore around the
fact that there is duplicate. And if
there are not too many of them, it's
probably not a big deal too. So you just
need to change it in a couple of places,
that's probably okay. But if you can if
you can avoid duplicates, definitely
definitely avoid them because duplicates
is often an overhead.
>> Yeah. And I'll reference again the
previous episode with Vlad Kongh on
balancing coupling and software design
because he references a lot of this in
that book and listeners who want to deep
dive into that could check that out as
well. So we've talked a lot about the
elements of complexity and how to
understand it. We've talked about some
design principles as it relates to code
health, but there's also processes that
you discuss in the book about helping to
maintain code health. Can you describe
what some of those elements are of
process or what those processes are that
help teams to either improve their code
health or maintain their code health?
>> Yeah, definitely. So I think one process
that I don't see being used a lot
outside of Google and Canva also uses
design docs a lot but I've seen a lot of
companies which do not seen a lot of
companies which kind of ignore this
upfront design and even has a negative
connotation right when you say upfront
design like it feels uncomfortable like
are we not agile anymore
>> well there's big upfront design and then
there's a little bit of upfront or just
enough right something tells me you're
advocating for just enough.
>> Yeah. And that's the case. So I would
argue and that's what Google practices
actually suggest that a bit of upfront
design actually helps you be more
productive and it actually makes the
process a bit more delightful too
because you don't need to delete as much
code as you would otherwise. So yeah,
having a bit of an upfront design is
definitely helpful and I would argue
that it's the best way to do trade-off
analysis.
>> And the best alternative to a design doc
in most cases is a one pager, which is
basically a small design doc.
>> It's a small design doc. Well, yeah. I
mean, you you talk about trade-offs.
Once you have an implementation, nobody
wants to talk trade-offs anymore,
especially once it's merged.
>> Yeah, exactly. But sometimes like the
product would push you in the in that
direction. You would need to talk about
trade-offs. They would become obvious.
>> Yeah. Interesting. Okay. So, what
differentiates a design doc from I'm
going to use the W word. You know, when
people think of, you know, waterfall,
they think of a massive specification
with every possible thing. But since
that's not what you're describing, you
talked about a one-pager, but you said
that's a very small design doc. But what
is a design dock? What goes in it? Well,
there are always pros and cons, right?
If we're talking about longer design
docs or shorter design docs, it depends
on like it it won't catch as many issues
if it's a shorter design, right? But at
the same time, the return on investment
may be the best if we're talking about
short design doc,
>> right? But if I'm a listener and I'm
saying, okay, I agree with you that I
should do some kind of design docs,
maybe not big design upfront, but some
design upfront, then what should I put
in these design docs?
>> Yeah. So there are pretty standard
templates there. You're just describing
some background about the project you're
about to do, goals, maybe non- goals.
You provide a quick overview of the
solution and maybe talk about some
details. Depends on whether it's a big
design doc or not that big design docks.
But I would argue that every design doc
should have at least some trade-off
analysis in it. I think that's the very
heart of design docs that you're making
decisions, right? Where will you make
that decision? Will you make it in a
design dock or will you make it in some
meetings or will you talk to
stakeholders one-on-one and then get out
of sync with each other over time or you
just to design like in your head or on
the whiteboard before coding? All these
alternatives have so many downsides that
it becomes pretty obvious once you write
this down and there is a trade-off table
in the design box chapter in the book
which clearly shows that design blocks
are absolutely the winner there.
>> Great. And I'll put a link in the show
notes to the episode that I hosted Chad
Michelle talking about lean software
systems engineering for developers and
one of the key concepts in that book is
the idea of gaining and maintaining a
shared understanding throughout the
project. And that seems like that
dovetales really well with what you're
describing with design documentations.
They help us gain and maintain that
shared understanding. Another aspect you
mention of process is code reviews. A
lot of people do code reviews, but maybe
you have some nuance perspective on what
exactly good code review entails. Why
should we do code reviews to ensure code
health? There are four goals for doing
code reviews. And interestingly, when I
first was doing good code reviewer
classes internally at Google, we had
just two. That's one thing that was
really surprising when I was writing
this book. Then I actually discovered
two more top level goals. I I can tell
you the story about this, but let's go
over the first ones too. The first the
most obvious goal is high quality,
right? You basically just need the
second pair of eyes. Two heads are
better than one. You've done something.
You definitely need to review it
yourself, but you also need somebody
else with a fresh eye to take a look and
catch something. If they have a
different expertise if they're more
senior than you, that's helpful, but
that's not necessary because fresh eye
actually helps a lot here. So many
problems even junior developer can catch
just because they didn't see this code
before. and do not have all the context
you have in your head as an author. The
second reason for doing code reviews is
knowledge sharing. And that's huge
because in our industry we so often
don't have the same context. If you go
to meetings and start talking about
solutions high level, you experience all
the time, right? People try to
understand what you're talking about and
just give you a bunch of garbage advice
just because they do not have any
details and they're trying to help you
but they really cannot. But code reviews
are very different because when you're
doing code reviews you have all this
context in front of your eyes. So you
have all the code all the code is there
and if something is missing you have an
author there who is happy to help you
provide you with all the context that
you need. So having the same context
being on the same page is very helpful
for knowledge sharing because now you
can having the same context you can
actually share what you think share what
you know share previous experiences and
all this stuff and that actually helps
you grow so much faster but there are
two other goals there which we didn't
have originally in the good code review
bureau classes internally at Google and
how I got to those goals is really funny
Because the original presentation, a
good code reviewer at Google, it had two
parts, three parts, but it had part for
the goals and it had a huge part for the
practical tips and tricks, which is
basically like 10 practical tips and
tricks Google has learned over two
decades doing like millions of reviews.
And when I was writing the book, I was
trying to do an experiment. Just try to
connect those practical tips and tricks
to the goals.
>> So you have two goals. You have around
10 practical tips and tricks. And you
try to see what goals do they help with.
And what I found out is that nearly half
of the practical tips and tricks didn't
address any of those two goals. M
>> and that's was something really
surprising and if you see this then you
can do two things right you can start
questioning the tips and tricks which
probably wouldn't be wise because that's
a lot of wisdom there like that Google
has accumulated over the decades another
option is to question the goals and
that's what I did and that's how I
discovered two additional goals and the
third one is psychological safety and
psychological safety is actually Let's
let's do the fourth one first because
it's simpler. The fourth one is delivery
speed. It's kind of obvious. You want to
optimize your code reviews for delivery
speed. You don't want to end up with
this analysis paralysis thing or you
don't want to do like perfect PR out of
this. There's no such thing as a perfect
PR. So yeah, delivery speed is
definitely another top level objective
or top level goal there. But there's
also one more that is not that obvious
which is psychological safety. And it
all goes back to another project that
was done internally at Google. Uh you
can find a lot of information about it
online which is named project Aristotle.
It was basically a research on Google
teams. I think over 100 teams
participated or something like this
trying to figure out what makes teams at
Google productive. And there were a
bunch of expectations what would come
out from this research. things like what
about complimentary skill sets or maybe
very good communication like whether you
have extroverts in your team versus
introverts but interestingly if you look
at the results of the research nothing
like that came up it doesn't affect team
productivity much but what does affect
team productivity much is psychological
safety first of all then the second
predictor in the list is reliability but
it's a distant second so psychological
safety by far exceeds any other thing if
we're talking about team productivity.
So you really need to have good
psychological safety climate in your
team if you want your team to be
productive and how it relates to code
reviews. Code reviews is oh wait a
moment let me let me explain
psychological safety a little bit.
Psychological safety is basically when
you feel safe to take risks in front of
your team. If you feel safe to look
stupid in front of a team like ask
stupid questions or just bounce off
weird stupid ideas looking stupid ideas,
right? So that's kind of a psychological
safety definition and code reviews
affect the psychological safety climate
a lot because code reviews is where you
you're faced with your errors more often
than anywhere else. I guess maybe design
docs is another thing but design docs
are like they're more high level you can
argue you you can talk about things like
as Lin was like saying like doc is cheap
right show me code so in code that's
where you will see the actual errors and
that's where you will either deal with
them professionally and we'll be open to
discuss it acknowledge them and just
build up the climate of psychological
safety or you're going to be defensive
not willing to talk about stuff and just
destroy psychological safety climate in
your team. So that's another third or
fourth goal of code reviews.
>> Well, as we wrap things up, were there
any surprising revelations or lessons
during the writing process? So I just
talked about code review and that was
really surprising for me to find out
that there are two more highle goals
because I was doing code review
presentation code review tech talks
probably more than any other tech talks
in my life and the fact that I only
found out that there are two more highle
goals only when writing the book that
was pretty surprising very unexpected
and yeah by the way I'm referring to
internal Google presentations a lot
here, but they're based mostly on
internal documentation that was open
sourced recently by Max Alexander. So
I'm not a whistleblower here. So I'm
sharing something that is already
present online. I'm just like
structuring it in slightly different
way. So yeah, I was really surprised
that I found two more highle goals
there. But a couple more things also
surprised me a lot. The first thing is
that I was holding so tight to John
Ahood's definitions of complexity causes
and complexity problems for such a long
time when I was working on a I mean it's
kind of organic because my university
course was based on John's work in a
large extent but as I was iterating on
the content these seven alternative
seven complexity causes were already
circulating in the content
of the university courses, but I wasn't
calling it complexity causes because it
was so much in my head that there are
two complexity causes, dependencies and
obscurity, and I must stick to it. But
that's not the case, right? Because
they're quite abstract. If you think
about dependencies and that's so
abstract and calling it how is it
helpful saying that dependencies is a
complexity cause even though I agree
mostly agree that you can track it down
to dependencies and obscurity but
pragmatically speaking if you want it to
be practical you want to be more
specific here and I think seven
complexity causes are actually much
better if we're talking about obscurity
untrue complex interfaces unfamiliarity
too any dependencies duplication and
unstable dependencies is much much more
practical and pragmatically better than
having just obscurity and dependencies.
So that's one thing that struck me that
I held tightly to those two dependency
or sorry complexity causes for such a
long time. And another thing is I guess
about deep interfaces. If you remember
John's work, he actually introduced the
term deep modules and if you look
through the Google group discussions
about this, you will find Jimmy, I
forgot his surname, some Jimmy was
critiquing John for not being specific
by what he actually means by deep
modules. And they had a very long
discussion there and they didn't resolve
it. And after some time I just jumped in
and we're talking with John about it
last year. And I think what we found out
is that John by himself is not sure what
he means by deep modules because he's
not sure whe they were talking about
implementation there or not talking
about implementation. And I had this gut
feeling when I was starting the book
that this need to be clarified. But I
didn't know what exactly would come from
it and actually redefining it and saying
okay let's let's talk about deep
interfaces and leave everything else to
saying like okay we don't want modules
to be dysfunctional that's a separate
topic let's just decouple it a little
bit and just focus on interfaces when
we're talking about depth that was uh
pretty big revelation
>> so when you say a deep interface versus
a shallow interface what exactly are you
describing
Yeah. So that's basically again value
for money. How much functionality does
the interface promise in turn for the
complexity of the interface. So you can
think of it as like uh functionality
divided by complexity of the interface.
>> So a narrow interface that does a lot
for you versus a broad interface that
does very little for you.
>> Exactly. Yeah.
>> Okay. Great. Well, this has been a great
exploration of your book, Arty. If
listeners want to learn more about you
and the book, is there a website they
can go to?
>> Yeah, definitely. You can go to
codeguardian.com.
>> Well, Arty, thank you so much for
joining me on the show.
>> Thank you very much. Thanks for having
me. This is Jeff Doolittle for Software
Engineering Radio. Thanks for listening.
>> Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net net to
provide feedback. You can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Common
License 2.5. Thanks for listening.